Guide to the Jack Lund Collection ARS.0045
Archive of Recorded Sound
Jack Lund Collection
1887-2009
ARS.0045
Lund, Jack H.
5345 items (570.33 linear ft.) Collection of disc recordings, tapes, books, magazines, programs, librettos, printed music and autographed programs and photographs.
Archive of Recorded Sound, Stanford University Libraries Stanford, California 94305-3076
The Jack Lund Collection contains personal papers of Jack Lund as well as numerous newspaper and magazine clippings, photographs, and music books. It also contains Lund's collection of classical music on 78 rpm discs, mostly in albums, 33 1/3 rpm long playing discs, and a small number of open reel tapes. The materials in this collection document the principal musical interests of Mr. Lund, i.e. vocal solo music, opera, careers and performances of specific singers and pianists, and the career of Arturo Toscanini. Since Mr. Lund mantained personal friendships with many musicians he admired, he acquired autographed photographs of these artists, and he regularly corresponded with them. The photographs and many of the letters from these musicians are included in the collection. As an avid reader of published articles and books on musical topics, Mr. Lund collected newspaper clippings and books about specific musicians, and he also corresponded with the authors of these writings. Letters received from these authors and a large number of clippings are also included in the collection. Some copies of journals and newsletters, which were included in the donated collection, have been retained in order to provide a broader context to Mr. Lund's musical interests and pursuits.
Arrangement note
The materials in the Jack Lund Collection have been divided into two categories: (1) print and photographic material and (2) sound recordings. The print and photographic materials have been organized into 6 series as follows: (1) Letters from Musicians and Their Associates; (2) Toscanini Files; (3) Concert Programs; (4) Music Books; (5) Photographi Materials; (6) Other Print Materials.
The commercially released open reels tapes and shellac and vinyl discs are being cataloged and shelved with other like materials in the Archive of Recorded Sound. The non-commercial tapes will be cataloged and stored in Stanford's off-site storage facility.
Biographical/Historical note
Jack H. Lund was born in San Francisco on January 10, 1913 but spent the early years of his life in Berkeley. He attended the University of California, Berkeley and graduated in the Class of 1935. During the Second World War he served in the army and achieved the rank of Major. Following the footsteps of his father, Jack Lund worked for the Friden Calculating Company for twenty-five years and became its Sales Promotion Manager before he retired in the 1960s. It was during Lund's retirement years that he was able to pursue his primary interests, tennis and music.
As an avid follower of tennis, Jack Lund attended 31 Wimbledon championships and 25 French championships, and he maintained friendships with many of the best known American tennis stars. Lund himself played tennis with the California Tennis Club until he was 91.
Jack Lund's musical interests were focused on classical music, particularly German lied and opera. He was also a great admirer of Arturo Toscanini, and in addition to attending many Toscanini concerts, he became a member of the Toscanini Society and collected significant amounts of related memorabilia. Lund built a massive record collection that featured the greatest classical singers of the time as well as performances of Toscanini. He attended many of the European music festivals and was a strong supporter of the San Francisco Opera and the San Francisco Symphony Orchestra. Through his attendance and support of musical events he established friendships with numerous prominent musicians and was particularly outgoing when musical artists came to perform in San Francisco. It was not unusual for Jack Lund to entertain his musical friends at his apartment which boasted beautiful views of the San Francisco Bay and Berkeley. He was a great admirer of Kirsten Flagstad, Gerard Souzay, and Ignaz Jan Paderewski, and he could count among his friends such singers as Aksel Schiotz, Dame Janet Baker, Elly Ameling and Jessye Norman, as well as pianist Dalton Baldwin. Lund also became friends with the esteemed French music teacher Nadia Boulanger, and at one point he sat in on her classes at Fontainebleau-- probably the only non-musician ever to do so.
Although Jack Lund never considered himself to be a musician, he spent much of his time keeping himself informed about the music world through reading, concert attendance and ongoing communication with artists and record collectors. Jack Lund died on November 27, 2009, and as per his request, there was no funeral or memorial.
Conditions Governing Access note
Collection is open for research. Listening appointments may require 24 hours notice. Contact the Archive Operations Manager.
Scope and Contents note
The Jack Lund Collection was bequeathed to Stanford University by Jack Lund, and the donation was executed by Karen L. Johnston shortly after Mr. Lund's death in 2009. The collection consists of 5345 items and a total of 570.33 linear feet. The materials document Mr. Lund's associations and friendships with a wide array of musicians in the U.S. and abroad, his activities in music organizations, and particularly his musical interests as demonstrated in the large number of recordings which he collected throughout his lifetime.
All of the paper and photographic materials in this collection are described in this finding aid. All of the sound recordings are being fully cataloged separately, and the bibliographic records can be found in WorldCat and the Stanford Libraries' database. In the local Stanford database the bibliographic records for recordings in this collection include the searchable subject heading "Jack Lund Collection."
Separated Materials note
The sound recordings in the Jack Lund Collection, contained in Boxes 16-97 and 99-137, have been separated from the rest of the collection materials and are being individually cataloged. The recordings are shelved in the Archive of Recorded Sound.
Indexing Terms
Boulanger, Nadia; Flagstad, Kirsten, 1895-1962; Norman, Jessye; Paderewski, Ignace Jan, 1860-1941; Toscanini, Arturo, 1867-1957; Conductors (Music); Operas; Pianists; Singers; Women music teachers
- Series 1: Letters from Musicians and their Associates
  - Alphabetical Document Files, 1970-2006; 17 folders (Box 1)
    Separated Materials note
    1 bundle of newspaper clippings about Kirsten Flagstad and 2 individual clippings about Ignaz Jan Paderewski have been removed from Folder 1.1.5 and placed in Oversize Folder 1 (Box 141)
    17 additional bundles of newspaper clippings have been removed from Box 1 and placed in Oversize Folder 2 (Box 141)
    1 additional oversize folder of letters and clippings related to Jessye Norman has been moved to Box 98
    Scope and Contents note
    11 file folders containing primarily letters from various musicians but also photographs, newspaper clippings and opera program boolets. The contents of individual folders are as follows:
    (1) Elly Ameling letters and postcards
    (2) Dalton Baldwin letters, photographs and a program booklet from the Festival de Versailles, 1977
    (3) David Bicknell, letters and other documents, 1981-1990
    (4) Letters from Mme. Marcel Dupre and photographs of Marcel Dupre and Madame Dupre
    (5) Kristen Flagstad and Ignaz Jan Paderewski clippings
    (6) Edouard Lobkowicz correspondence, related letter from Kevin King, and related newspaper clipping
    (7) Ivor Newton letters, postcards and other related material
    (8) Jessye Norman letters and cards
    (9) Blanche Thebom letter, and page from Musical America with record advertisement
    (10) Notes and letter related to Diana Ross with 4 black and white photos
    (11) Aksel Schiotz letters and other documents
    (12) Letters and postcardsfrom various musician friends, including Gerd Schiotz and Gerard Souzay
    (13) Letters from various music-related people and personal friends, written between 1959 and 2001
    (14) Music related societies
    (15) Miscellaneous documents and journals
    (16) Letters, clippings and other materials related to various music events and people; letter to Edward Baron Turk; travel itinerary
    (17) Opera program books
    Five program books from San Francisco Opera performances
    Ameling, Elly; Baldwin, Dalton; Dupré, Marcel, 1886-1971; Flagstad, Kirsten, 1895-1962; Lobkowicz, Edouard, 1926-2010; Newton, Ivor; Norman, Jessye; Paderewski, Ignace Jan, 1860-1941; Ross, Diana, 1944-; Schiøtz, Aksel, 1906-1975; Thebom, Blanche
  - Nadia Boulanger and Conservatoire américain de Fontainebleau, 1968-1979; 3 folders (Box 139)
    Various items related to Nadia Boulanger and the Fontainebleau School of Music in four folders:
    (1) Letters and cards from 1968 to 1970, from Boulanger and others; folder includes various menus from L'Ecoles d'Art Americaines
    (2) Letters and postcards from people connected to L'Ecoles d'Art Americaines, including Boulanger; concert programs, brochures and various handwritten notes
    (3) Letters and postcards from people connected to L'Ecoles d'Art Americaines, including Boulanger; concert programs, brochures and various handwritten notes
    (4) Newspaper clippings, newsletters and copies of the summer course catalog for Fontainebleau Schools of Music and Fine Arts, 1968, 1969 and 1971 (Golden Jubilee)
    Boulanger, Nadia; Ecoles d’Art Américaines.
  - Letters Inserted in Recording Containers, 1985 January 24; 1 folder (Box 139)
    Folder (5): Letter from Manny to Jack Lund. Had been inserted in box with a 5" tape reel of early performances by Gerard Souzay. Tape reel is located in Box 7 of this collection.
- Series 2: Toscanini Files
  Toscanini, Arturo, 1867-1957
  - Toscanini Files, Part I, 8 folders (Box 138)
    The following clippings have been removed from Box 138 and placed in Oversize Folder 1 (Box 141):
    9 bundles of newspaper clippings (photocopies)
    1 illustrated article clipping (original)
    Part I of the Toscanini files contain letter-size documents pertaining to the career of Arturo Toscanini:
    (1) Brochures
    (2) Concert programs
    (3) Newspaper clippings
    (4) Toscanini Society
    (5) NBC broadcast list, Maroth #2 [original]
    (6) Published articles
    (7) The Maestro, 1969
    (8) The Maestro, 1970-1975 (selected issues)
  - Toscanini Files, Part II, 4 folders (Box 140)
    One letter-sze folder and three legal size folders containing Toscanini-related material as follows:
    (1) NBC Symphony schedules
    (2) Toscanini Society newsletters, record trade lists, record-related articles
    (3) Correspondence with collectors of Toscanini recordings
    (4) Brochures, complete discography of Toscanini recordings, other record lists related to Toscanini recordings
    NBC Symphony Orchestra.; Toscanini, Arturo, 1867-1957
- Series 3: Concert Programs, folders (Box 2)
  - Bay Area Concert Programs and Recording Lists, 1928-1979; 3 folders (Box 2)
    Three folders of programs from concerts of various artsists, primarily pianists and singers, and one copy of Revue de Musicologie with information about French music research at the University of California, Berkeley
    Box also contains two card files: (1) 5" x 8" cards listing contents of recorded tapes; (2) 3" x 5" cards, in an interior box, listing recordings with dates.
  - Bay Area Opera and Symphony Concert Programs, 2 small boxes, 7 1/4" x 10 1/2" x 4" (Box 3)
    Two small boxes of various concert programs from performances sponsored by organizations such as the San Francisco Opera Association, Oppenheimer Concert Series, San Francisco Symphony Orcehstra
  - Ballet and Mime Theatre Files, 4 folders (Box 98)
    Souvenir program books from mime performances of Marcel Marceau, Folies Bergere, performances of various ballet companies, and the Philadelphia Orchestra
    (2) Marcel Marceau (5 program books)
    (3) American Ballet Theatre; Sadlers Wells Ballet; Philadelphia Orchestra (4 program books)
    (4) Russian ballet companies (8 program books)
    (5) Folies Bergere (1 program book)
    (6) Jessye Norman: additional letters and oversize clippings (removed from Box 138)
    American Ballet Theatre.; Marceau, Marcel; Philadelphia Orchestra.; Sadler's Wells Ballet.
- Series 4: Music Books (Box 4)
  Boulanger, Nadia; Toscanini, Arturo, 1867-1957
  - Music Books, 15 books (Box 4)
    Jack Lund's library included over 150 books, primarily on musical topics. The books were checked against the Stanford Music Library's holdings, and all duplicate books in the Lund Collection were removed. All of the remaining books from the Lund Collection were retained and shelved in the Music Library.
    Various clippings from newspapers and journals, letters and some photographs had been placed inside of many of the books. Those inserted materials have been removed from the books and placed in file folders each of which is labeled according to the book from which that folder's materials were taken.
    Book titles and related information:
    Seltsam, William H. Metropolitan Opera Annals. New York: H.W. Wilson, 1947. Autographed by the author
    Sackville-West, Edward, and Shawe-Taylor, Desmond. The Record Guide. London: Collins, 1951. Inscribed to Jack Lund and dated by Desmond Shawe-Taylor
    Leonie Rosenstiel. Nadia Boulanger: A Life in Music. New York: W.W. Norton, 1982
    Steane, J.B. The Grand Tradition: Seventy Years of Singing on Record. New York: Charles Scribner's, 1974.
    Sachs, Harvey. Toscanini. Philadelphia: J.B. Lippincott, 1978
    Haggin, B.H. The Toscanini Musicians Knew. New York: Horizon Press, 1967. Autographed by the author
    Marsh, Robert Charles. Toscanini and the Art of Orchestral Performance. Philadelphia: J.B. Lippincott, 1956
    Taubman, Howard. The Maestro: The Life of Arturo Toscanini. New York: Simon and Schuster, 1951
    Dyment, Christopher. Felix Weingartner: recollections & recordings. Triad Press Biographical Series no. 5, 1976
    Antek, Samuel. This Was Toscanini. New York: Vanguard Press, 1963
    Homnmage a Edouard Branly. Association des Amis d'Edouard Branly. Inscribed to Jack Lund by Marion Tournon-Branly
    Gerhardt, Elena. Recital. London: Methuen & Co., 1953
    Haggin, B.H. Music in the Nation. New York: William Sloane, 1949. Inscribed to Jack Lund by the author
    Morris, Manuel. The Recorded Performances of Gerard Souzay: A Discography. New York: Greenwood Press, 1991. Inscribed to Jack Lund and dated by the author
    Newton, Ivor. At the Piano: The World of an Accompanist. London: Hamish Hamilton, 1966.
    Folders:
    [1] Clippings etc. filed in Gerhardt: Recital
    [2] Clippings etc. filed in Taubman: The Maestro
    [3] Clippings etc. filed in Haggin: Music in the Nation
    [4] Clippings etc. filed in Marsh: Toscanini and the Art of Orchestral Performance
    [5] Clippings etc. filed in Haggin: The Toscanini Musicians Knew
    [6] Clippings etc. filed in Sachs: Toscanini
    [7] Clippings etc. filed in Steane: The Grand Tradition
    [8] N. Boulanger: clippings etc. filed in the Rosenstiel biography
    [9] Clippings etc. filed in Antek: This Was Toscanini
    [10] Clippings filed in Morris: Souzay
    [11] Clippings filed in Dyment: Weingartner
    [12] Materials filed in Newton: At the Piano
    [13] Book Lists: Folder contains 3 lists: (1) Lund Books Retained; (2) Lund Books Duplicatesl (3) 15 additional published volumes on various musical topics: Arturo Toscanini (5 vols.), Nadia Boulanger (1 vol.), singers, other musicians, and a record guide. Several of these books are autographed by their respective authors.
  - Clippings and Other Inserts, 12 folders (Box 4)
    Inserted in the books in this collection were various clippings, photographs, letters and other materials, specifically related to the books into which these items had been placed. The inserted materials have been removed from the books and filed in folders as descrbied below. Oversize items, such as newspaper clippings, have been placed in an oversize folder.
    Folders are as follows:
    (1) Clippings, etc. filed in Gerhardt: Recital
    (2) Clippings, etc. filed in Taubman: The Maestro
    (3) Clippings, etc. filed in Haggin: Music in the Nation
    (4) Clippings, etc. Clippings, etc. filed in Marsh: Toscanini and the Art of Orchestral Performance
    (5) Clippings, etc. Clippings, etc. filed in Haggin: The Toscanini Musicians Knew
    (6) Clippings, etc. filed in Sachs: Toscanini
    (7) Clippings, etc. filed in Steane: The Grand Tradition
    (8) Nadia Boulanger clippings, etc. filed in Rosenstiel biography
    (9) Clippings, etc. filed in Antek: This Was Toscanini
    (10) Clippings, etc. filed in Morris: Souzay
    (11) Clippings, etc. filed in Dyment: Weingartner
    12) Clippings, etc. filed in Newton: At the Piano
    The following clippings have been removed from their original folders and placed with oversize materials in Oversize Folder 2 (Box 141):
    "Death of Elena Gerhardt" (from Folder 4.4.1)
    "A Great Lieder Singer" (from Folder 4.4.1)
    "Supreme Lieder Singer" (from Folder 4.4.1)
    "Second Thoughts on Toscanini" (from Folder 4.4.2)
    "Wanda Toscanini Horowitz, Pianist's Bulwark, Dies at 90" (from Folder 4.4.6)
    "A Role for Records? Purists Say: Yes, Just Listen" (from Folder 4.4.7)
    "Masters' Voices" (from Folder 4.4.7)
    "Reviewed by Arthur Bloomfield" (from Folder 4.4.7)
    "Teacher of the Greatly Gifted" (from Folder 4.4.8)
    "Everybody's Music Teacher" (from Folder 4.4.8)
    "Book Review: Nadia Boulanger: A Life in Music" (from Folder 4.4.8)
    "Books: Nadia Boulanger: A Life in Music" (from Folder 4.4.8)
    "The Gift to Be Simple" (from Folder 4.4.8)
- Series 5: Photographic Materials
  - Photographic Materials, 4 folders containing photographs, slides and one autographed concert program (Box 5)
    Photographs, photographic images from concert programs, newspapers, or postcards, primarily of opera singers and pianists, mostly black and white, and most are autographed
    General photographic materials have been divided into two groups by size and placed in the first two folders accordingly:
    (1) 40 small, black and white photographic images and 6 small, color photographs, 3" x 4 1/2" to 5" x 7" with most being 3 1/2" x 5 1/2"
    (2) 60 large, black and white photographic images and 1 large color photograph, 5 1/2"" x 8 3/4" to 9 3/4" x 10 3/4" + 3 color slides + 1 concert program with image of Marian Anderson on cover, autographed
    (3) Pablo Casals Masterclass, University of California, Berkeley, 04/23/1962 to 05/04/1962: 20 small, black and white photographs 4 1/2" x 3 1/4" + 3 ticket stubs + publicity brochure
    (4) Nadia Boulanger and Conservatoire américain de Fontainebleau: 54 photographs, some color, 3 1/2" x 5" to 9 1/2" x 7" + 1 black and white negative
    Boulanger, Nadia; Casals, Pablo, 1876-1973; Conservatoire américain de Fontainebleau.
- Series 6: Other Print Materials
  - Friden News, 1952-1971; 1 folder (Box-folder 98/1)
    One folder containing 5 issues of Friden News, ranging from May 1952 to February 1971.
  - Librettos, 1 small box, 7 1/4" x 10 1/2" x 4" (Box 3)
    Assorted opera librettos, some from specific opera companies such as San Francisco Opera and Chicago Civic Opera.
  - Nan's Programs 1887-, 1887-1900; 1 bound volume (Box 3)
    Bound volume is a scrapbook containing numerous varied concert programs, playbills and newspaper clippings dating from 1887 to 1900. Some items are autographed. Handwritten on the cover of the volume: "Nan's Programs 1887-"
  - Other Artist Autographs, 1906-1963; 1 folder (Box-folder 3/1)
    1 folder containing various concert programs, brochures, index cards and other fragments with autographs of musicians. Also included is an unsigned photograph of Jack Lund with Walter Damrosch
    Damrosch, Walter, 1862-1950
  - Newspaper Clippings: Flagstad, Paderewski, 1932-1963; 1 folder (Box-folder 1/5)
    Photocopies of various newspaper clippings related to the career activities of soprano Kirsten Flagstad and pianist Ignaz Jan Paderewski.
    Oversize newspaper clippings related to Flagstad and Paderewski are located in Oversize Folder 1 (Box 141).
  - Chevaliers du Tastevin, 1998 December 9; 1 oversize leaf in oversize folder labeled Box 6 (Box 6)
    Highly decorative certificate in full color, 18 1/2" x 24 1/2" proclaiming Jack Lund a member of the Chevaliers du Tastevin and dated 9 Decembre 1998.
  - Oversize clippings, etc., 1 folder (Box 141/Oversize Folder 1)
    3 folders of oversize clippings: (1) Kirsten Flagstad clippings, removed from Box 1; (2) Ignace Jan Paderewski clippings removed from Box 1; (3) Arturo Toscanini clippings removed from Box 138
  - Oversize clippings, etc., 1 folder (Box 141/Oversize Folder 2)
    Oversize clippings removed from folders in Series 1 and Series 4:
    From Series 1:
    17 bundles of newspaper clippings removed from Box 1 and placed in this folder
    From Series 4: